

## **PROFILE**

Focused, passionate, and strategic Hotel General Manger with 18+ years of leadership role, offering diverse and accomplished experience in the hospitality industry. Reputation for building stronger teams, delivering higher gains, and optimizing organization's capabilities for decades. Sought –after for deep strategic insight to improve Guest experience, revive business growth, reverse decline in revenues, and slash expenses.

## MANOJ KUMAR

## CORPORATE GENERAL MANAGER

-Entrepreneurial Spirit. Explorative by Nature-

ሬ

+91 -9113280616

KETHANA RESIDENCY, VIGNAN NAGAR | BANGALORE | INDIA



#### **AREAS OF EXPERTISE**

- Pre Opening Specialist
- Operations Management
- Business Mapping
- Strategic Planning
- ROI Analysis
- Contract Negotiations
- Budgeting & Cost Controls
- Brand Management
- Communications
- Recruitment & Development
- Online Channel Management
- Reservations & Distributions
- P&L Management
- Conflict Resolution
- Digital Marketing | Social Media | Content Strategist
- Stakeholder Management

#### **QUALIFICATION**

- MASTER IN BUSINESS ADMN IBMI INSTITUTE, BERLIN GERMANY | 2020
- PG in Hotel Management MICHIGAN UNIVERSITY, LANSING | USA - 1999
- Bachelor Degree
   Hotel Management
   BANGALORE UNIVERSITY,
   INDIA 1999

#### **HOTEL PMS**

- OPERA PMS
- IDS 4.2FIDELIO
- MICROSOFT OFFICE

## **WORK EXPERIENCE**

#### **CORPORATE GENERAL MANAGER**

## RED CARPET HOSPITALITY - INDI RED GROUP | BANGALORE | OCT18 - MAR 21

Red Carpet Hospitality is a Hotel Management Consultancy operating in South of India. Managing cluster hotels with a room inventories of 500+ and extensive food & beverage operations.

- Oversight of front office, food & beverage, housekeeping and the spa with a focus on guest experience, service levels, appearance and adherence to group SOPs
- Recruitment and ongoing management, scheduling and employees' performance management.
- Creating departmental objectives with seasonal variation and incentives.
- Analysing data to evaluate customer satisfaction and trends to identify areas of improvement.
- Maximizing occupancy at the highest rates and upselling ancillary hotel services.
- Performing on-going staff training products, services, fire safety, HACCP and customer service.
- Accountable for MIS Reports as well as revenue forecasts for the Board.

## **Key Achievements**

- Generating a GOP of 38%, Kitchen 76% with wages accounting for 26% of expenditure.
- Restructured departmental staffing and saved approximately USD 16K annually in payroll cost.
- Developed monthly F&B promotions both offline (In-house) and Online to increase sales.
- Increased the sleeper dinner from 21% to 28% running team member incentives.
- Incrementally increased revenue by 30% per month between August 2018 to February 2019
- Reduced beverage cost by .75% to bring in line with budgets.
- Achieved 94% employees' satisfaction and reduced attrition rate.
- Achieved 90.2% Guest satisfaction from Hotel Experience between 2018 to 2021, and 94% satisfaction rate from event management.

#### PRE-OPENING CLUSTER GENERAL MANAGER

## ELIANA HOTEL & MAGNOLIA HOTEL | ETHIOPIA | NOV 2014 – AUG 2018

Managed 2 Four Star African Brand Hotel properties with 88 Keys +86 Keys inventories, Multiple F&B outlets, Fitness Centre, Spa, Function Halls & Media Wall.

- Garnered regional excitement for the African Brand, Ignited a surge of opening deal for the classy operations, strong sales, and marketing.
- Built high performance customer focused team, unifying the distinct perspective of multifunctional team to achieve positive change. Developed an innovative talent recruitment and training program that attracted fresh graduate and younger talent pool open to learning a new language.
- Consistently grew market fair share within 6 months of opening, through deep competitive market assessment, forecasting, cost control and market execution strategy.
- Quickly positioned hotel at the break-even point within a year by maximizing monthly sales of USD
   1.6 Million, controlling cost, and launching various services that maintained rooms capacity.

## **PERSONAL STRENGHT**

- SELF MOTIVATED PROFESSIONAL
- QUICK ADAPTABILITY
- INTERPERSONAL SKILLS
- INNOVATIVE
- RESULT ORIENTED
- MULTITASKING
- SOLUTION ORIENTED
- EASILY RELATE TO PEOPLE
- MEETING EXPECTATIONS
- VOLUNTEERING
- SOCIALITE
- WORKS IN TEAM
- CAN DO ATTITUDE

#### **CERTIFICATIONS**

UNIVERSITY OF LONDON | 2021

• BRAND MANAGEMENT
LONDON BUSINESS SCHOOL

AMITY BUSINESS SCHOOL DUBAI | 2020

- CONTENT MARKETING
- MEDIA & PUBLISHING
- EMAIL MARKETING
- PRODUCT MANAGEMENT
- DIGITAL MARKETING

MICHIGAN UNIVERSITY | 2020

• BUSINESS NEGOTIATION STRATEGIES

GEORGE TOWN UNIVERSITY SPORT TOURISM | 2014

#### **RECOGNITIONS**

CERTIFICATE OF EXECLLENCE
TRIPADVISOR | ELIANA HOTEL | 2017

CERTIFICATE OF EXECLLENT SERVICE AWARD — IGAD, EAST AFRICA ELIANA HOTEL | ETHIOPIA | 2016

AFRICA UNION'S PREFERED HOTEL ELIANA HOTEL | ETHIOPIA | 2016

LUXURY RESORT AWARD
CONDE NAST TRAVELLER AWARD
COCO OCEAN REORT & SPA
GAMBIA | 2010, 2011, 2012

CERTIFICATE OF APPRECIATION
CEO OF ALMUROOJ HOTELS
DOHA | QATAR | 2009

#### **WORK EXPERIENCE**

#### **HOTEL MANAGER**

## CORP EXECUTIVE HOTEL | HMH HOSPITALITY | QATAR | AUG '2012 - SEPT '2014

Operationally lead a 4-Star resort with leisure facilities. Accountable with annual budget of USD 2M, Recruitment, SOP development, HACCP, Brand Compliance, supplier management and operational set-up. Direct reporting Chairman of the Company.

- Collaborated with project management team and owners in renovating rooms and leisure facilities in each project phase.
- Created Business Plan (revenue forecasts, budgets staffing, P&L) for 2012 to 2014.
- Defined the advertising, pricing strategy and secured strategic partnership with Corporate, TOs, NGOs and Governments.
- Worked with engaged management team to leverage revenue from point of sales.

## **PRE-OPENING HOTEL MANAGER**

## LE GRAND HOTEL | ALMUROOJ GROUP | QATAR | MAY 2006 - JULY 2012

A Premier 4 Star Boutique with 120 Rooms & Suites, an 80 cover fine dining restaurant, and 75 seater coffee shop and conference & event facilities up to 350pax.

- Administered as a pre-opening Hotel Manager along with CEO to fuel business development opportunities from ground-up through high profile networking and relationship building, including government authorities. Reporting directly to CEO and parallel reporting to CFO.
- Led 108 employees from 8 Nationality to effectively execute them as a drivers of positive culture by re-energizing a focus on measurable goals that cascaded throughout the organisation during my tenure.
- Strategically placed sales agents on retention model in the buyers' market to optimize sales.
- Bolstered positive financial by liaising with Corporates, Tour Operators, Government Sectors, Qatar Sport Authority, Embassies
- Incorporated vital value additions like upgrading room choices during lean period, revamping toiletries and bedding to overcome competition.

#### **ROOMS DIVISION MANAGER**

#### ELITE SUITES HOTEL | MANAMA | BAHRAIN | MAY 2006 – MAY 2007

Luxury 4 Star Dry Hotel with 255 Rooms & Suites, 3 F&B Outlet, and Banqueting Space & Spa

Accountable for Rooms Division operations, administered strategies to maximize revenue through effective pricing management tools. Controlled cost to optimize profit canter. Responsible for operations per the local laws for fire & safety and HACCP guideline.

#### **ROOMS DIVISION MANAGER**

## ROYAL OCHIRD HOTEL PARK PLAZA | BANGALORE, INDIA | MAR 2004 - APR 2006

Park Plaza's first Luxury Brand Hotel in South of India, having 197 Rooms, Club Rooms and Suites Multiple Food & Beverage Outlet and Spa Operations

Charged with priming this organisation for profitability customer acquisition through channel partners and change catalyst leadership, repaired relationship with OTs through strategic alliance building. Assisted General Manager in daily operational functions.

#### ASSISTANT FRONT OFFICE MANAGER

#### LEELA PALACE KEMPINSKI HOTEL | BANGALORE | FEB 2001 - FEB 2004

An Ultra Luxury Palace Hotel & Convention Centre managed by Kaminski Brand having 415 Rooms, Suites and Club Rooms, 7 F&B Outlets, Large Banqueting & meeting Rooms.

#### FRONT OFFICE DUTY MANAGER

#### WINDSOR MANOR SHERATON & TOWER | BANGALORE | APR 99 – JAN 01

A 5 Star Hotel designed in British styles having 240 Rooms and Suites with separate tower block, 9 F&B Outlets and Banqueting space.

# HOTEL MANAGEMENT OPERATION TRAINEE WINDSOR MANOR SHERATON & TOWER | BANGALORE

A 5 Star Hotel designed in British styles having 240 Rooms and Suites.